Finding aid to the Laurenus Clark Seelye papers CA.MS.00001
Smith College Archives
Laurenus Clark Seelye papers
1820-1995
1875-1924
Smith College Archives
Seelye, Laurenus Clark, 1837-1924.
CA.MS.00001
14.792 linear feet (28 containers)
Laurenus Clark Seelye was the first president of Smith College. His papers contain biographical material, correspondence, sermons, speeches, lectures, publications, photographs and family papers of Henrietta Chapin Seelye. Correspondents include President Marion LeRoy Burton, Harry Norman Gardiner, Arthur L. Gillett, John M. Greene, Mary Augusta Jordan, William H. Lanning, Alice (Lord) Parsons, Herbert A. Wilder, Andrew Carnegie, President William McKinley, and John D. Rockefeller, Jr, among others.
Biographical / Historical
Laurenus Clark Seelye was the first president of Smith College. Born on September 20, 1837, in Bethel, Connecticut, he was the youngest child of Abigail Taylor Seelye and Seth Seelye, who married in 1817. Seth Seelye was a merchant, farmer, and deacon. Seelye's sisters, Hannah and Elizabeth, were not educated. L. Clark and his brothers, Thomas, Samuel, Julius, and Henry, were all educated. Three of the sons, Samuel, Julius, and L. Clark, went on to become ministers, Thomas became a physician, and Henry a farmer and later an attorney. Julius served as the president of Amherst College. Seelye most likely attended the Center District School in Bethel. He was schooled in Woodbury, attended the Old Hadley Academy, and afterwards spent some time in Danbury to complete his education. At the age of twelve he started home-schooling under his brother Samuel. He entered Union College at the age of sixteen where he received a B.A. and graduated as valedictorian with highest honors. After Union, he attended Andover Seminary but left due to ill health. He traveled throughout the Mediterranean and across Europe in hopes of getting well; while in Germany, he decided to complete his education in Heidelberg.
Scope and Contents
The Laurenus Clark Seelye Papers consist primarily of correspondence and written sermons and lectures. Other types of materials represented in this collection include news articles, photographs, manuscripts and published works, notebooks, scrapbooks, journals, and memorabilia.
The Smith College correspondence includes letters between President Marion LeRoy Burton, Harry Norman Gardiner, Arthur L. Gillett, John M. Greene, Mary Augusta Jordan, William H. Lanning, Alice (Lord) Parsons, and Herbert A. Wilder. The correspondence provides a good record of the early days of Smith College, as well as a look at the people after whom Smith College buildings and monuments are named. Names of note in the non-Smith College correspondence include Andrew Carnegie, President William McKinley, and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Topics cover everything from money to religion. One weakness of the correspondence is that quite a few of the first names of correspondents are not apparent or are completely unknown.
The series of lectures comprises the largest portion of history in this collection. All of these works were written by Seeleye and give insight into his religious and secular views. The sermons range from 1859-1910 and include the city in which the sermon was given. Speeches are divided into religious, Washington's Birthday, and secular categories. Seeleye's lectures are divided into subject. His lectures on English Literature were given between 1864 - 1875.
Arrangement
The correspondence, ranging in date from 1860 - 1934, is divided by family and professional life. The professional correspondence is divided into the following sections: Smith College (1872-1934), Non-Smith College (1876-1924), and Employment opportunities (1862-1872).This collection is organized into six series:
I. Biography
II. Correspondence
III. Sermons/Speeches/Lectures
IV. Publications
V. Photographs
VI. Henrietta Chapin Seelye
Additional Formats
Images from this collection are also available online as part of the Five College Archives Digital Access Project.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown
Smith College -- presidents; Seelye, Laurenus Clark, 1837-1924.; Seelye, Henrietta Chapin.; Smith College--Presidents.; Jordon, Mary A. (Mary Augusta), 1855-1941.; Burton, Marion Le Roy, 1874-1925.; Gardiner, H. Norman (Harry Norman), 1855-1927.; Gillett, Arthur L.; Greene, John Morton, 1830-1919.; Parsons, Alice Tullis Lord.; Carnegie, Andrew, 1835-1919.; McKinley, William, 1843-1901.; Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison), 1874-1960.; Smith College. Office of President.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHY, 1854-1995; 2.04 linear feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series covers Seelye's life in terms of his family history, Union College, Smith life and memorabilia (including inauguration and retirement), his life achievements and opinions, and his death. The folders are arranged alphabetically. Most of the material is newspaper articles. Other materials include a scrapbook, class notebooks, publications, and various memorabilia.
  - Bethel, CT, 1911-1991; undated (Box 280, Folder 1)
  - Book dedication, 1864 (Box 280, Folder 2)
  - Church; prayer, 1894-1915; undated (Box 280, Folder 3)
  - Death
    - Obituaries, 1924 (Box 280, Folder 4)
    - Tributes; announcements (news clippings), 1924-1937 (Box 280, Folder 5)
    - Tributes; announcements (dated), 1924-1934 (Box 280, Folder 6)
    - Tributes; announcements, undated (Box 280, Folder 7)
  - Family history, 1899-1984; undated (Box 280, Folder 8)
  - Finances: trip to Europe; devotional image, 1862 (Box 280, Folder 9)
  - Funeral: William Allen Neilson's address, 1924 (Box 280, Folder 10)
  - Honorary degree from Union College, 1913 (Box 280, Folder 11)
  - Marriage and anniversaries, 1863-1943 (Box 280, Folder 12)
  - Milk receipt, 1923 (Box 280, Folder 13)
  - News clippings (biographical), 1896-1940 (Box 280, Folder 14)
  - News clippings (misc.), 1901-1929; undated (Box 280, Folder 15)
  - Opposition to women's suffrage, 1883-1995 (Box 280, Folder 16)
  - Union College: "Seelye Seelye and His Alma Mater", 1934 (Box 280, Folder 17)
  - U.S. Christian Commission, 1864 (Box 280, Folder 18)
  - Union College
    - Orations and essays, 1854 (Box 281, Folder 1)
    - Science, 1856 (Box 281, Folder 2)
    - Hickok's Theology, 1857 (Box 281, Folder 3)
    - Theology (Box 281, Folder 4)
  - Smith life and memorabilia
    - Beginning of Smith College, 1875-1925; undated (Box 282, Folder 1)
    - Calling card, 1875-1910 (Box 282, Folder 2)
    - Class of 1909 alumnae booklet, 1923 (Box 282, Folder 3)
    - Class of 1913, 1916-1923 (Box 282, Folder 4)
    - Friendship Calendars, 1908-1909 (Box 282, Folder 5)
    - Graduation weeks, 1901-1910; undated (Box 282, Folder 6)
    - Inauguration, 1875 (Box 282, Folder 7)
    - Inauguration: publications, 1875 (Box 282, Folder 8)
    - Retirement: news clippings, 1908-1915; undated (Box 282, Folder 9)
    - Retirement: publications, 1910 (Box 282, Folder 10)
    - Smith College tributes, 1898-1925; undated (Box 282, Folder 11)
    - Trips abroad, 1901 (Box 282, Folder 12)
    - Holy Bible, 1879 (Box 280.1)
  - Miscellaneous oversize: Elizabeth Seelye sampler; portrait of Elsie Bowland by Henrietta Seelye, 1893; unknown (Box 303)
  - Scrapbook (Box 304)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE, 1860-1925; 0.63 linear feet
  This series is divided into four subseries. The correspondence from Family members is arranged alphabetically by the first name of the person to whom the letter was sent. Correspondence that has to do with Seelye's professional life at Smith College is arranged alphabetically by last name. Each folder classifies the person as an alumna, a parent, or an associate. Correspondence from Non-Smith College people are also arranged alphabetically by last name and cover his outside activities, notable people, and parishioners. The subseries Employment opportunities contain correspondence that Seelye received from various institutions asking him to consider working for them.
  - Family
    - To Cousin Fanny from Seelye Seelye, 1923(?) (Box 283, Folder 1)
    - To Hannah Seelye from a friend, 1860 (Box 283, Folder 2)
    - To Julius and Libby (Elizabeth James) Seelye from Seelye Seelye, 1861-1869(?) (Box 283, Folder 3)
    - To Julius Seelye from Mother (Abigail Taylor Seelye), 1864 (Box 283, Folder 4)
    - To Julius and Libby from Elizabeth Seelye, 1863 (Box 283, Folder 5)
    - To Dr. Laurens Hickok from Robert Booth, 1860 (Box 283, Folder 6)
    - Middle East and Europe, 1860-1862 (Box 283, Folder 7)
    - To Millie from Mother and Father, 1875; undated (Box 283, Folder 8)
  - Smith College
    - Abbott, Elsie (Bourland) '95, 1910 (Box 284, Folder 1)
    - "An Alumna of Smith College", 1917 (Box 284, Folder 2)
    - Anderson, Grace E. '94, 1923 (Box 284, Folder 3)
    - Andrews, Hannah Dunlop '04, 1920 (Box 284, Folder 4)
    - Burton, Marion LeRoy, 1915 (Box 284, Folder 5)
    - Byrd, Mary E., 1895-1904 (Box 284, Folder 6)
    - Clarke, Elizabeth Crocker Lawrence '83, 1923 (Box 284, Folder 7)
    - Converse, Clara Adra '83, 1900-1920 (Box 284, Folder 8)
    - Cook, Caroline, 1907 (Box 284, Folder 9)
    - Cutler, Anna Alice '85, 1913 (Box 284, Folder 10)
    - De Forest, Charlotte Burgis '01, 1919 (Box 284, Folder 11)
    - Dike, Dr., 1892 (Box 284, Folder 12)
    - Dimock, Mr. and Mrs. George, 1902-1915 (Box 284, Folder 13)
    - Early History of Smith College: responses, 1915-1925 (Box 284, Folder 14)
    - Employment opportunities, 1872-1934 (Box 284, Folder 15)
    - Finances, 1900-1904 (Box 284, Folder 16)
    - Franklin, Ruth, 1909 (Box 284, Folder 17)
    - Gardiner, Harry Norman, 1913 (Box 284, Folder 18)
    - Gillett, Arthur L., 1917 (Box 284, Folder 19)
    - Greene, John M., 1873-1916 (Box 284, Folder 20)
    - Hazen, Charles Downer, 1914 (Box 284, Folder 21)
    - Jordan, Mary Augusta, 1910 (Box 284, Folder 22)
    - Lanning, William H., 1910 (Box 284, Folder 23)
    - Lewis, Alice Bradbury '86, 1918 (Box 284, Folder 24)
    - Lyman, Edward Hutchinson Robbins, 1897 (Box 284, Folder 25)
    - Martin, J., 1910 (Box 284, Folder 26)
    - Park, Edwards A., 1872 (Box 284, Folder 27)
    - Parsons, Alice (Lord) '97, 1914 (Box 284, Folder 28)
    - Pearson, Lucy Wright '86, 1920 (Box 284, Folder 29)
    - Senate Bill 290, 1907 (Box 284, Folder 30)
    - Smith, Mary Gove '02, 1904 (Box 284, Folder 31)
    - Taplin, Edith (Smith) '05, 1915(?) (Box 284, Folder 32)
    - Thomas, Gail (Tritch) '06, 1906 (Box 284, Folder 33)
    - Varney, Alice M. '07 (and other members of '07), 1912 (Box 284, Folder 34)
    - Walker, Mary Manning (1881-1884), 1917(?) (Box 284, Folder 35)
    - Whitaker, Ellen (Comins) '91, 1916 (Box 284, Folder 36)
    - Wilder, Herbert A., 1896 (Box 284, Folder 37)
    - Woods, Norma (Hoblit) '10, 1923 (Box 284, Folder 38)
  - Non-Smith College
    - Amherst College, Class of 1869, 1919 (Box 284, Folder 39)
    - Carnegie, Andrew, 1905 (Box 284, Folder 40)
    - Clubs, 1876-1878 (Box 284, Folder 41)
    - Coolidge Home Committee, 1920 (Box 284, Folder 42)
    - Gere, Henry S., 1907 (Box 284, Folder 43)
    - Hartwell, Mr., 1900 (Box 284, Folder 44)
    - Harvard University, 1897-1907 (Box 284, Folder 45)
    - Kent, C.A., 1913 (Box 284, Folder 46)
    - Kneeland, Martin D., 1913 (Box 284, Folder 47)
    - Lee, Sarah White, 1895 (Box 284, Folder 48)
    - Marble, Mrs., 1924 (Box 284, Folder 49)
    - Massachusetts Biographical Society, 1920 (Box 284, Folder 50)
    - McClure, James, 1918 (Box 284, Folder 51)
    - McKinley, President William, 1899 (Box 284, Folder 52)
    - McLean, Charlotte F., 1909 (Box 284, Folder 53)
    - Palmer, Alice F., undated (Box 284, Folder 54)
    - Richmond, Charles A., 1914 (Box 284, Folder 55)
    - Rockefeller, John D., Jr., 1901-1905 (Box 284, Folder 56)
    - Talbot, Mrs. B.F., undated (Box 284, Folder 57)
    - Taylor, Joseph Wright, 1878 (Box 284, Folder 58)
    - Williams College, 1897 (Box 284, Folder 59)
    - Williston, Belvin Thomas, 1917 (Box 284, Folder 60)
  - Employment opportunities
    - Bridgeport, CT, 1862 (Box 284, Folder 61)
    - Springfield, MA; resignation, 1862; 1865 (Box 284, Folder 62)
    - New York, 1864 (Box 284, Folder 63)
    - Amherst, MA, 1865 (Box 284, Folder 64)
    - New Haven, CT, 1866 (Box 284, Folder 65)
    - Boston, MA, 1867; 1872 (Box 284, Folder 66)
- SERIES III. SERMONS/SPEECHES/LECTURES, 1859-1923; 4.17 linear feet
  This series is the largest in the collection. It covers Seelye's numerous SERMONS/SPEECHES/LECTURES from the time he was a pastor to the last years of his life. The dated Sermons are arranged chronologically and include the city in which the sermon was given. The undated sermons are arranged alphabetically by title or the first sentence of the sermon. Seelye traveled throughout the country giving sermons, including to Chicago; Bethel, CT; Albany, NY; Springfield; Amherst; Brookline; Northampton; Norwich; Brooklyn; Easthampton; and Boston. Speeches are further divided into subseries of religious, Washington's Birthday, and secular. Both the religious and secular speeches are arranged alphabetically by title and/or subject; Washington's Birthday speeches are arranged chronologically. Lectures are divided into English Literature and the History of Education. The English lectures cover the years when Seelye was an English professor at Amherst College. Most of the lectures are about the history of education at women's colleges. Both subseries are arranged alphabetically by title and/or subject. The majority are handwritten by Seelye; the rest are typed with various handwritten corrections.
  - Dated
    - Chicago, IL, 14 Aug 1859 (Box 285, Folder 1)
    - Bethel, CT, 30 Sep 1860 (Box 285, Folder 2)
    - Albany, NY, 21 Oct 1860 (Box 285, Folder 3)
    - UNIDENTIFIED, 11; 12 Dec 1860 (Box 285, Folder 4)
    - Bethel, CT, Aug 1862 (Box 285, Folder 5)
    - Albany, NY, Sep 1862 (Box 285, Folder 6)
    - Albany, NY, Oct 1862 (Box 285, Folder 7)
    - Springfield, MA, Dec 1862 (Box 285, Folder 8)
    - Albany, NY, 22 Dec 1862 (Box 285, Folder 9)
    - Springfield, MA, 25 Jan 1863 (Box 285, Folder 10)
    - Springfield, MA, Feb - Jul 1863 (Box 285, Folder 11-16)
    - Springfield, MA, Sep 1863 (Box 285, Folder 17)
    - Springfield, MA, 4 Oct 1863 (Box 286, Folder 1)
    - Springfield, MA, Nov - Dec 1863 (Box 286, Folder 2-3)
    - Springfield, MA, Jan - Jul 1864 (Box 286, Folder 4-10)
    - Springfield, MA, Sep - Nov 1864 (Box 286, Folder 11-13)
    - Springfield, MA, 11 Dec 1864 (Box 286, Folder 14)
    - Springfield, MA, 21 Feb 1865 (Box 287, Folder 1)
    - Springfield, MA, 26 March 1865 (Box 287, Folder 2)
    - Springfield, MA, 24 May 1865 (Box 287, Folder 3)
    - Springfield, Amherst, MA, 7 Jan 1866 (Box 287, Folder 4)
    - Amherst, MA, Feb; Mar 1866 (Box 287, Folder 5)
    - Springfield, MA, 6 May 1866 (Box 287, Folder 6)
    - Brookline, MA, 5 Jan 1868 (Box 287, Folder 7)
    - Northampton, MA, 2 Feb 1868 (Box 287, Folder 8)
    - Amherst, MA, 1 Nov 1868 (Box 287, Folder 9)
    - Amherst, Springfield, MA, Feb 1869 (Box 287, Folder 10)
    - Amherst, Agricultural College, MA, Mar 1869 (Box 287, Folder 11)
    - Amherst, MA, 13 Nov 1870 (Box 287, Folder 12)
    - Amherst, MA, 29 Jan 1871 (Box 287, Folder 13)
    - Norwich, CT, Amherst, MA, Oct 1871 (Box 287, Folder 14)
    - Amherst, MA, 7 Feb 1872 (Box 287, Folder 15)
    - Amherst, MA, 4 Mar 1872 (Box 287, Folder 16)
    - Brooklyn, NY, 12 May 1872 (Box 287, Folder 17)
    - Amherst, MA, 17 Nov 1872 (Box 287, Folder 18)
    - Brookline, MA, 11 May 1873 (Box 287, Folder 19)
    - Amherst, MA, 15 Jun 1873 (Box 287, Folder 20)
    - UNIDENTIFIED, 15 Mar 1874 (Box 287, Folder 21)
    - Easthampton, MA, 21 Nov 1875 (Box 287, Folder 22)
    - Boston, MA, 6 Jan 1878 (Box 287, Folder 23)
    - Springfield, MA, 29 Sep 1879 (Box 287, Folder 24)
    - Sermons, Jun 1879 (Box 288, Folder 1)
    - UNIDENTIFIED, Jun 1880 (Box 288, Folder 2)
    - UNIDENTIFIED, Jun 1879; Jun 1880 (Box 288, Folder 3)
    - UNIDENTIFIED, Jun 1881-1889 (Box 288, Folder 4-12)
    - Sermons, 1890-1910 (Box 289, Folder 1-21)
  - Undated
    - "Aristotle..." (Box 290, Folder 1)
    - "Art thou..." (Box 290, Folder 2)
    - "The Books of the Bible..." (Box 290, Folder 3)
    - "Canon Apostle" (Box 290, Folder 4)
    - "The First Principle..." (Box 290, Folder 5)
    - "From This..." (Box 290, Folder 6)
    - "Good and Upright..." (Box 290, Folder 7)
    - "I Believe..." (Box 290, Folder 8)
    - John 4:7-8 (Box 290, Folder 9)
    - John 4:29 (Box 290, Folder 10)
    - John 9:5 (Box 290, Folder 11)
    - Kings 14:6 (Box 290, Folder 12)
    - "Knowledge Through Abstract..." (Box 290, Folder 13)
    - Lenten Season (Box 290, Folder 14)
    - Life of Christ (Box 290, Folder 15)
    - Luke 12:15 (Box 290, Folder 16)
    - Luke 18:29, 30 (Box 290, Folder 17)
    - Matthew 8:4 (Box 290, Folder 18)
    - Matthew 22:40 (Box 290, Folder 19)
    - "On Communion" (Box 290, Folder 20)
    - "Prayer at the Opening of a War" (Box 290, Folder 21)
    - Philippians 1: 21 (Box 290, Folder 22)
    - Samuel 23:17 (Box 290, Folder 23)
    - Partial sermons (Box 290, Folder 24-28)
    - Fragments (Box 290, Folder 29-31)
  - Speeches: religious (Box 290)
    - "The Burial of the Unknown Soldier", undated (Box 291, Folder 1)
    - Chapel Talks
      - "Character...", undated (Box 291, Folder 2)
      - Christmas, 1916 (Box 291, Folder 3)
      - Notes; ideas, undated (Box 291, Folder 4)
      - Prayers (Commencement), undated (Box 291, Folder 5)
      - Prayers (Thanksgiving), undated (Box 291, Folder 6)
      - Prayers, 1889; 1923; undated (Box 291, Folder 7)
      - Railroad Crisis, undated (Box 291, Folder 8)
      - Recording, undated (Box 291, Folder 9)
      - Religious subjects, undated (Box 291, Folder 10)
    - Commencement: chapel prayer, 1920 (Box 291, Folder 11)
    - Communion: Northampton, 1914 (Box 291, Folder 12)
    - "Community Religion", undated (Box 291, Folder 13)
    - Congregationalist Church, undated (Box 291, Folder 14)
    - Connecticut Valley Association Unitarian Ministers, undated (Box 291, Folder 15)
    - Crucifixion, undated (Box 291, Folder 16)
    - Day of Prayer
      - Colleges, 1881 (Box 291, Folder 17)
      - Colleges, 1888 (Box 291, Folder 18)
      - Job, undated (Box 291, Folder 19)
    - "Educated Women as Missionaries", 1888 (Box 291, Folder 20)
    - Funerals
      - E.L.B., 1890 (Box 291, Folder 21)
      - Gov. William Washburn, undated (Box 291, Folder 22)
      - Mrs. Wellenhour, undated (Box 291, Folder 23)
    - Marriage Service, undated (Box 291, Folder 24)
    - Massachusetts Bible Society, 1871 (Box 291, Folder 25)
    - Memorial Address: Rev. Robert Woods, 1909 (Box 291, Folder 26)
    - Memorial Day Address, 1887 (Box 291, Folder 27)
    - Memorial for President William McKinley, 1901 (Box 291, Folder 28)
    - New Year's Sermon, 1909 (Box 291, Folder 29)
    - Northampton Old Church, 1908 (Box 291, Folder 30)
    - "On the Character and Qualities...", 1877 (Box 291, Folder 31)
    - Trask, Rev. John L.R., 1888 (Box 291, Folder 32)
    - The Union Chapel: 25th Anniversary, 1902 (Box 291, Folder 33)
    - Unitarian & Congregational Ministers, undated (Box 291, Folder 34)
  - Speeches: Washington's Birthday
    - 1894-95 (Box 291, Folder 35-36)
    - 1897 (Box 291, Folder 37)
    - 1899-1900 (Box 291, Folder 38-39)
    - 1902 (Box 291, Folder 40)
    - 1905 (Box 291, Folder 41)
    - 1908 (Box 291, Folder 42)
    - 1917 (Box 291, Folder 43)
    - 1919 (Box 291, Folder 44)
    - 1921-22 (Box 291, Folder 45-46)
    - undated (Box 291, Folder 47)
  - Speeches: secular
    - Abbot Academy, 1879 (Box 292, Folder 1)
    - Bryn Mawr: 25th Anniversary, 1910 (Box 292, Folder 2)
    - Chicago Fire, 1871 (Box 292, Folder 3)
    - Commencement Address: Latin, 1923 (Box 292, Folder 4)
    - Commencement Speech, 1899 (Box 292, Folder 5)
    - Gov. Calvin Coolidge, 1920 (Box 292, Folder 6)
    - "Evils of Making Money Without Work", undated (Box 292, Folder 7)
    - Gordon, (Senator) General John B., undated (Box 292, Folder 8)
    - "The Higher Education...", 1888 (Box 292, Folder 9)
    - July Fourth, undated (Box 292, Folder 10)
    - Liberty, undated (Box 292, Folder 11)
    - Lincoln, Abraham, undated (Box 292, Folder 12)
    - miscellaneous individuals, 1916; undated (Box 292, Folder 13)
    - Mount Holyoke College, 1903 (Box 292, Folder 14)
    - Music festival, undated (Box 292, Folder 15)
    - "On Laughter", undated (Box 292, Folder 16)
    - Response to Dr. Hall's Speech, undated (Box 292, Folder 17)
    - "The Song of Songs", undated (Box 292, Folder 18)
    - Sophia Smith Centennial, 1896 (Box 292, Folder 19)
    - Spanish-American War, 1898 (Box 292, Folder 20)
    - Taxation: "The College and the City", undated (Box 292, Folder 21)
    - Taxation: Exemption, 1907 (Box 292, Folder 22)
    - Temperance, undated (Box 292, Folder 23)
    - Union College, 1913 (Box 292, Folder 24)
    - Valedictory Speech: Smith Club, NY, 1910 (Box 292, Folder 25)
    - Wallace, Rodney, undated (Box 292, Folder 26)
    - "Why a Girl Should Go to College", undated (Box 292, Folder 27)
    - "Women in Letters", 1900 (Box 292, Folder 28)
  - Lectures: English Literature (c., 1864-1875)
    - Appleton's Cyclopaedia, 1875 (Box 293, Folder 1)
    - Bunyan, undated (Box 293, Folder 2)
    - Celtic History, undated (Box 293, Folder 3)
    - "The Celtic Spirit", undated (Box 293, Folder 4)
    - Thomas Chatterton, undated (Box 293, Folder 5)
    - Chaucer, undated (Box 293, Folder 6)
    - Dryan, undated (Box 293, Folder 7)
    - "The Elizabethan Era: Sir Phillip Sidney", undated (Box 293, Folder 8)
    - Goldsmith, undated (Box 293, Folder 9)
    - Samuel Johnson, undated (Box 293, Folder 10)
    - Milton, undated (Box 293, Folder 11)
    - "Miracle Plays", undated (Box 293, Folder 12)
    - "Origin of the English People", undated (Box 293, Folder 13)
    - "Ossian and Macpherson", undated (Box 293, Folder 14)
    - "The Puritans...", undated (Box 293, Folder 15)
    - "The Roman Period", undated (Box 293, Folder 16)
    - "The Saxon Period", undated (Box 293, Folder 17)
    - Shakespeare, undated (Box 293, Folder 18)
    - "Style", undated (Box 293, Folder 19)
    - Swift, undated (Box 293, Folder 20)
    - Traces of the Celt in the Anglo Saxon, undated (Box 293, Folder 21)
    - "The Troubadours", undated (Box 293, Folder 22)
    - "What We Mean by a History of English Literature", undated (Box 293, Folder 23)
    - "Writers who have no part...", undated (Box 293, Folder 24)
    - Fragments of lectures, undated (Box 293, Folder 25-27)
  - Lectures: History of Education
    - Higher Education for Women, undated (Box 294, Folder 1-3)
    - History of Education, undated (Box 294, Folder 4)
    - Idea of a College
      - Collegiate Method, undated (Box 294, Folder 5-6)
      - "Has the College...", undated (Box 294, Folder 7)
      - "The Idea of a Collegiate...", undated (Box 294, Folder 8)
      - "Modern Universities", undated (Box 294, Folder 9)
      - President Eliot's Address, undated (Box 294, Folder 10)
      - "Wisdom is that...", undated (Box 294, Folder 11)
    - "The largest library in the world...", undated (Box 294, Folder 12)
    - Fragments of lectures, undated (Box 294, Folder 13)
- SERIES IV. PUBLICATIONS, 1859-1925; 0.83 linear feet
  This series is arranged alphabetically by title and/or subject. The materials are both manuscripts and published works, from editorials to magazine articles to books. The main subseries is Seelye's Early History of Smith College. (The original letters can be found in Series II. CORRESPONDENCE, Box 5 Folder 13.) The Drafts make up the bulk of the material.
  - "Antiquity of Celtic Literature" (published), 1870 (Box 295, Folder 1)